نَسْعَلُ اللهَ عَزُّوْاَجَلْ أَلَّا يَدَعْ بَيْنَ نَا وَلَا فِيْنَا،،
اَحَدً اِلَّا بِذَنْبٍ مَغْفُوْرْ وَسَاعٍ مَشْكُوْرْ
وَنَسْعَلُ اللهَ عَزُّوْاَجَلْ أَنْ َيَجْعَلَنَامِنْ كُلِّ هَماٍ فَرَجَا وَمِنْ كُلِّ ضِيْقٍ مَخْرَجَا وَمِنْ كُلِّ عُسْرٍيُسْرَاَ
We talked about the, attention Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين)
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه  gave to a Ibadaat(عبادات),
we talked about the importance he gave to Salaat(صلاة)
and we missed the part on Taraweh(تراويح), we start with that.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه came into the Masjid(مسجد) in Ramadan(رمضان),
and he found them scattered around the Masjid(مسجد).
This man is praying on his own,
this man is leading a Jama'at(جماعة) of  three or four or five.
This one is leading a Jama'at(جماعة) of 10, this one is alone, all over the Masjid(مسجد).
And there Qira'at(قرأة ) was confusing each other.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه said: "I will combine them all, behind one Imam(اِمَام)."
Rather than have everyone do their own thing, let them all pray together.
So, he appointed Obaeye Bin Ka'abرضي الله عنه, the scholar of Qur'an, the Sahabi(صحابي) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
from the people of Madina to lead Salaat-Ut-Taraweeh(صلاة التراويح).
He came the next day and he saw the Muslims praying in Jama'at(جماعة) in cohesion, so he said;
نِعْمَتِ الْبِدْعَةْ هَذِهِ، اَوْ نِعْمَ الْبِدْعَ هَذِهِ
This is a good Bid'ah( بدعة), this is a good Bid'ah( بدعة).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was happy to see that the Muslims are now praying together
rather than the disorganized way, it was happening before in the Masjid(مسجد)
and this quote by Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه , is mentioned frequently
and it's always brought up as an evidence to support,
whenever someone or somebody would do something new in religion.
So, is it truly a Bid'ah( بدعة)?
Did Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) really innovate?
Or he was speaking in a figurative sense, that this is something good that's what he meant.
Well let's look at the history of Salah-At-Taraweeh(صلاة التراويح).
Is Salah-At-Taraweeh(صلاة التراويح) something that was started by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) or did it exist before?
In the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ some would pray at home
and some would pray in the Masjid(مسجد).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came into the Masjid(مسجد) in Ramadan(رمضان) and he started praying.
The Sahabah(صحابه) who were there obviously joined Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, it was a Jama'at(جماعة) of Salah-At-Taraweeh(صلاة التراويح), in the Masjid(مسجد),
the next day more people poured in.
The third day more people, the fourth day the Masjid(مسجد) was packed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ on the fifth day didn't show up.
And then he told the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
أَمَّا بَعْدََ فَإِنَه’ لَمْ يَخْفَ عَلَيَّ مَكَانَكُمْ
وَلَكِنِّيْ خَشِيْتُ أَنْ تُفْرَضَ عَلَيْكُمْ فَتَعْجَزُوْا عَنْهَا
I did not want this to become a mandatory Salah(صلاة) on you.
What will happen, if Rasool Allah ﷺ keeps praying it in the Masjid(مسجد) as a Jama'at(جماعة)
and Sahabah(صحابه) are joining him all the time?
It would turn into something that is mandatory
and Rasool Allah ﷺ wants Taraweeh(التراويح) to remain as a voluntary act.
So, he said that's why I stopped leading the Salah(صلاة) in the Masjid(مسجد)
not because leading it in Jama'ah(جماعة) was wrong
but because I don't want it to become mandatory on you.
Therefore, Salah-At-Taraweeh(صلاة التراويح) existed in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, what Umar(عُمَر) did was, revived something that was already there.
He just revived, something that was already done by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Because even in the time Umar(عُمَر) Jama'aat(جماعات) were happening
but there were more than one Jama'ah(جماعة), they were scattered around.
So, he wanted to bring them,
so basically what Umar(عُمَر) did was combined the Jama'aat(جماعات) into one Jama'ah(جماعة), that's all.
So, this cannot be used as evidence that you're allowed to invent things in Sharia(شريعة)
but you are allowed to improve the way things are happening,
within the boundaries of the Sharia(شريعة), not to change anything in Shariah(شريعة).
But to improve the way, you practice it.
For example, we are praying in our Masajid(مساجد) Salaat-Ul-Jama'at(صلاة جماعة).
All right, we added an improvement to that and that's now we're using loudspeakers
something that they didn't use in the old days, we have the Mics, we have the speakers,
it is to improve our Salah(صلاة) of Jama'at(جماعة)
to make it easier to make it more beneficial for the people.
We didn't really change anything in the format of the Salah(صلاة) itself.
We just added something to it that is not actually a part of the Ibadah(عبادة)
and that is something that is absolutely legal and allowed.
You can call it an innovation, but it's not an innovation in religion.
So, I hope that the concept is clear.
We'll move on to the next section, and that is the economic crisis that occurred
during the time of  Umar Bin  Khattab رضي الله عنه .
And this is called Aam-Er-Ramadah(عام الرمادة), the year of the Ramadah(الرمادة), the Ashes.
And this was the 18th year of Hijrah(هجرة),
a few years into the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of  Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه,
the sky withheld its rain, and the Arabian Peninsula sunk into a famine.
They were dependent on the scars rain that they receive.
And they didn't receive anything that year.
So, it was said that wild beasts were so hungry they started attacking humans,
the cattle that the Arabs or the tribes owned were dying.
They would say a man would have this goat and it is so skinny, so he would slaughter it,
and would barely be able to eat it, because it's so disgusting.
And the Bedouins started coming in flocks to Madina
to come to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه asking him for help,
and Umar(عُمَر) has nothing to give them.
So, you have these refugees in Madina, thousands of them,
the count was 60,000, Bedouins who flocked to Madina.
And when we say 60,000 in those days, that's a huge number.
Keep in mind that the population of the earth at that time was very low.
Possibly didn't reached the billion mark yet.
So, the population was very scars.
So, you have 60,000 in those days, it means a lot, in today's terms.
And all of these refugees were coming to Madina thinking that the Khalifah(خليفه) has a solution for them.
And the Khalifah(خليفه) was as hungry as they are…
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was having this meal with a Bedouin.
He had for him crushed bread in butter.
So, he is eating with this Bedouin.
So, the Bedouin would take the piece of bread
and he would pass it on the rim of the plate, to wipe all of the butter that is stuck to the plate
and he would eat.
He would take the next piece of bread and pass it along the rim to absorb all of the butter in there
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is watching him.
And then he said: It seems that you haven't had any butter for some time.
The man said: Yes, Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I never had butter or oil.
And I never saw anybody eat it for a very, very long time.
He was so hungry…. and, and butter was part of their diet, see
animal shortening, or oil that comes from vegetable or vegetable sources, such as
olives, or other seed, that they would grind,
Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) what type of oil that they would have in that time.
But definitely, they had olive oil, which was an integral part of their diet
because of poverty and because the amount that they would eat was so low, your body needs fat, you know, now
because we eat so much, everybody tells us that fat is not good for you,
fat is not good for you, you're not supposed to have any fat.
However, you're supposed to have about 20% fat in your diet.
That's the right amount of fat that you should have in your diet.
The thing is, because we're having so much of it,
the physicians are telling us to stay away from it.
In those days, because they were having so less of it, they had to eat more
their bodies needed that fat because you have to have fat in your body.
So, for them olive oil and fat was an important part of their diet.
This man is saying that I haven't seen fat or oil in a very, very long time.
When Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه saw that, he made an oath
that he is not going to taste meat, butter.
He's not gonna taste it, until the Ummah(امة) eats it and the historian say;
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, stuck to his word and fulfilled his oath.
And until he made sure that the Ummah(امة) are having sufficient amount of food
that is when he started eating it again.
He used to say;
كَيْفَ يَعْنِيْنِيْ شَئْنُ الرَّعِيَّهْ إِذَا لَمْ يَمَسَّنِيْ مَا يَمَسُّهُمْ
How can I be concerned with my people, if I don't go through what they're going,
I need to feel their pain, I need to feel their suffering.
And that's why after you fast the month of Ramadan(رمضان),
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells you to give the Zakaat-Ul-Fitr(زكواة الفطر) Sadaqat tul fitr(صدقه الفطر)
because you have experienced the hunger that the poor go through.
So, you finish your fasting with giving out food to make them happy on the Day of Eid.
The Sahabah(صحابه) used to say that the color of the face of Umar(عُمَر) changed
in the year of Ramadah(رمادة).
It became very dark and thin because of the food that he was eating,
he restricted his diet to dry bread
Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) how old it is and he would dip it in oil or vinegar
and that's all he would have, no meat, no butter.
You can see that it's a very limited diet and it's unhealthy
and that's why the body of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) changed
and the color of his face changed to the extent that Aslam(أسلم) said;
كُنَّا نَقُوْلُ لَوْ لَمْ يَرْفَهْ الله عزوجل اَلْمَحَلَّهْ عَامَ الرَّمَادَهْ
لَظَنَنَّا أَنَّا عُمر يَمُوْتُوْ هَمًّا بِاَمْرِالْمُسْلِمِيْنَ
Aslam(أسلم) said: We used to think that if Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ did not elevate
the hunger of the year of Ramadah(رمادة), Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would have died
because of his concern for his people.
He wouldn't be able to carry on long in that fashion,
he would have died,
but it was the blessing of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ that it only lasted for a year and then it was lifted.
He was very strict even with his children, he saw his young child, one of his boys,
having some fruit in his hand, one piece of fruit Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
بَخِنْ بَخِنْ  اِبْنِ اَمِيْرُ الْمُومِنِيْنَ يَأْ كُلُوْ بِتِّيْخَ
The son of Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) is eating fruits, while the Muslims are hungry
and he wanted to take that fruit from his son and the son just ran away,
his child just ran away and he was just crying.
You know, the child was crying, my father wants to take away from me this fruit,
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), that's very difficult on a father to do.
And he's pursuing this child, he wants to take it away from him.
Until, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was told that your child actually bought it.
With a handful of Nawah(نواة), date seeds.
So, actually he bought it, otherwise Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would have taken that fruit from his son.
So, he even place restrictions on his family.
Yani(يعني) it was very difficult for you to turn down your children when you know they're hungry
and they want something to eat,
you know, you would give them the best, you would prefer them over yourself.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) here is trying to take away, snatch away that fruit from his young child.
And with children, you know, they don't understand this,
this child was crying, was weeping.
And he had to run away and then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was stopped
and they told him that he actually bought it, so let him have it.
So, he applied the same rules that would apply to the rest of Ummah(امة), on himself.
And he lived the way they were living.
They're not eating butter, I'm not gonna have butter,
they're not eating meat, I'm not gonna have meat.
And by the way, this wasn't the condition on over the Muslim world.
This was just in the Arabian Peninsula.
The rest of the Muslim world, were not really affected by this,
I mean history books tells us that this was something confined to the Arabian Peninsula.
We mentioned the refugee camps.
So, they opened up camps for the refugees 60,000 in total,
almost two thirds of them died because of hunger and diseases.
First of all these Bedouins are not used to the climate of Madina.
They come from a very pure and pristine environment.
The desert is very clean and pure.
You know, for example, you would find that the lowest ratio, or existence of germs and bacteria is in deserts
because nothing can really live it's very dry and hot,
so it doesn't support these forms of life.
So, it's a very healthy environment is very tough and difficult.
But it's healthy,
while in Madina you have in those days they were swamps in Madina because it was agricultural land.
So, there were swamps and there was Hummah(همًا) in Madina.
And some scholars would interpret it today as breakouts of malaria
because it says in the books of history, it was a fever that would always break out in Madina,
so they would say that it was possibly malaria because of the swamps
that were in Madina because of the farm land.
So, Madina wasn't a healthy environment.
Even the the Muhajiroon( مهاجرون) when they came from Makkah to Madina they all fell ill
and we know of the poetry of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Bilal Ibn Rabah رضي الله عنهم,
when they were feeling home sick, they wanted to go back to Makkah
because of the epidemic climate that existed in Madina and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
أَللَّهُمَّ حَبِّبْ إِلَيْنَا الْمَدِيْنَهْ كَحُبِّنَا المَكَّهْ أَوْ أَشَدَّ حُبَّا
O Allah make us love Madina, like we love Makkah or more
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) suddenly all of the Sahabah(صحابه) loved Madina more than Makkah
and that became their choice of residence
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر), Uthman(عثمان), Ali(علي)
they could have went back to Makkah, when Makkah was opened
but they chose to stay in Madina,
when they disliked it, in the beginning.
They didn't want to be in Madina, they were all singing these lines of poetry longing to go back to Makkah
but because of the Dua(دُعَا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ every Mo'min(مؤمن) today loves Madina.
Abu Hurairah رضى الله عنه said: May Allah have mercy on Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
I saw him the year of Ramadah(رمادة).
By the way the meaning of Ramadah(رمادة) when I said ashes, it was so hot and dry
that when the wind is blowing in your face, it is as if it's blowing ashes in your face
so that's why they called it Aam-Er-Ramadah(عام الرمادة).
So, Abu Hurairah(أبوهريره) said: I saw him carrying two sacks on his back
and oil in his hand, and he's carrying it to the refugee camps.
And then he saw me, he said: Where did it come from Abu Hurairah(أبوهريره).
He said: Not from far away.
And then I joined in to help him.
So, we went and saw a new group that just came in,
they were 20 of them from the tribe of Muharib(محارب).
So, Umar(عُمَر) asked them: Why did they come?
They said: Al-Juhud(ألجحد), hunger brought us
and then they pulled out roasted leather of dead animals that they were eating,
they would rip off the leather from dead animals and eat it.
They would cook that leather and eat it.
That was how hungry they were.
And they would crush bones.
So, they showed us this white powder, Crushed bones that, they would just swallow.
That was how hungry they were!
when they showed that to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he took off his Ridaah(رداع),
and he started cooking for them, until they were full.
Malik Bin Al-Aos(مالك بن ألأوس) he says:
لَمَّا كَانَ عَامِ الرَّمَادَةْ قَدِمَ عُمر عَلى قَوْمِيْ وَهُمْ مِئَةْ بَيْتَ، فَنَزَلُوا الْجَبَّانَةْ
فَكَانَ عُمر: يُطْعِمُ النَاسَ مَنْ جَاءَه’ وَمَنْ لَّمْ يَأْتِ أَرْسَلَ اِلَيْهِ الدَّقِيْقَ وَالتَّمْرُ وَالْأَدْمُ إِلَى  مَنْزِلِهْ
Malik Bin Aos(مالك بن ألأوس) he said: Umar(عُمَر) came to our camp
and he provided us with food
and the ones who did not come, he sent to them dates and flour and bread, he would send it out to them.
فَكَانَ يُرْسِلُ إِلَى قَوْمِيْ بِمَا يُصْلِحُهُمْ شَهْرًا بِشَهْرَا,
And He رضي الله عنه would send enough rations for a month
and he would also visit the ill among them and he would provide the coffins to the dead.
And Malik Bin Aos(مالك بن ألأوس) said that death was spreading like wildfire among our people.
At one particular moment, I saw Umar(عُمَر) praying Janazah(جنازة) on 10 bodies.
And when the famine was over, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told them: Go back to your land.
And I will provide you with transportation.
And he ensured that everyone reached home safely.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), you know all of this work.
This is very time consuming how would Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) do it.
They would say: He would pray Ishaa(عشاء), go back home and start Qiyaam-Ul-Lail(قيا م اليل),
praying, praying, praying, and then he would go and make his nightly patrols visiting these camps
and then he would spend the day with them.
That was his schedule, it wasn't the nine to five job, it was 24/7.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sent letters to the different Muslim states,
Egypt, Iraq, Ash-Sham(ألشام), asking for urgent emergency help.
Because the problem was in the Arabian Peninsula.
He sent a letter to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
He said: You See me and my people dying and you and your people are enjoying the luxuries of life.
فَوَا غَوْثَاهْ وَا غَوْثَاهْ,
Help me fast, help me fast.
See, the problem happened in Arabia
and it became so bad that now people were dying and there was a time lag.
Yes! Things are going to start coming from the other states but
the problem was already so bad in Arabia that many people were dying.
See, that was the problem.
Things were fine in Egypt and Iraq and Ash-Sham(ألشام)
but by the time the help came in, many people already died.
And in those days they didn't have weather forecast, to tell them
that rain is not going to come for months, so you can plan for it.
It was something that just happened and they have to plan on the spot
so he sends this letter to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) asking for urgent help.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) sent him a letter back and said;
أتاك الغوث
Help is on its way.
Help is on its way!
I will send you caravans the front will be in Madina and the end of it will be in Egypt
and he sends him a caravan of a 1000 camels loaded,
he sends him 20 ships loaded
and he send them 5000 garments that was the help or aid that came from Egypt
and then from Iraq he received 1000 camels,
Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(ابوعبيدة عمرو بن جراح) sent him 4000 loaded camels,
so when Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) came to Madina, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) appointed him
to distribute all of the aid that came from Syria.
So, Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) he distributed it
and then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) gave him 40,000 Dirham(درهم), he gave it to him,
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) refused to accept these,
he said: We're fine, we're okay, we don't need it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him: Take it. He said: I don't want it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ offered me such money when I didn't need it or want it,
but then Rasool Allah ﷺ told me: To take it.
So, I'm telling you to take it.
As long as you're not looking forward to that money,
as long as your heart is not attached to this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
if Halal(حلال) money comes to you, accept it.
So, he gave it to Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) as a gift and a reward for his efforts.
Even though Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) said: I don't need it.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) was willing to volunteer.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wanted to pay him for his efforts.
Muawiyah Bin Abi Sufiyan( معاويه بن ابي سفيان), sent 3000 camels,
so now the pain and suffering was being elevated.
However, as I said: Many people already died
but because of the aid that was coming in, things were improving.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: If this famine would extend
I would put every hungry person with somebody who is wealthy
because people don't die on a half full stomach.
If somebody is having a full meal, I will pair them with somebody who has having nothing.
So, they will share their meal so everyone will have half a meal.
Umar(عُمَر) said: Nobody will die if they're having half a meal,
that was his plan if this would have extended but Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدالله) it didn't.
The Muslims were making Dua(دُعَا),
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) said; I would see my father always repeating this Dua(دُعَا).
اَللَّهُمُّ لَا تَجْعَلْ هَلَاكَ اُمَّتْ مُحَمَّدْاِلَى يَدِي
O Allah don't make the Ummah(امة) of Muhammad(محمد) parish on my hands, under my authority
I'm the one who is governing now,
I'm the one responsible for their affairs. Don't let them die in this time.
Don't let the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ die under my hands
and that is when, Umar Bin Khattabرضي الله عنه took Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبدالمطلب) with him to Assalaat-Ul-Asqaa(الصلاة استسقاء).
And he said:
اَللَّهُمَّ إِنَّا كُنَّانَتَوَسَّلُإلَيْكَ بِنَبِيِّنَا ﷺفَتَسْقِيْنَا,
وَإِنَّانَتَوَسَّلُ إِلَيْكَ بِعَمِّ نَبِيِّنَا فَاسْقِنَا قَالَ :يَسْقَوْنَ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
when Rasool Allah ﷺ was alive we used to make Waseela(وصيلة) through him that You (الله) give us rain.
Now, since he passed away we asked You(الله) through his Uncle Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبدالمطلب) to give us rain
and Allah سبحانه تعالى sent down rain on them.
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) stopped the application of the punishment of stealing.
So, no hands were amputated during that year.
Some people say that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) what he has done,
is he stopped applying the Hadd(حدّ).
It wasn't really that he stopped applying it.
What happened was, there was never a case, where it qualified for punishment
because Rasool Allah ﷺ says, and this Hadith(حديث) is in Musnad Abdur-Razzaq(مسند عبدالرزاق)
لَا يُقْطَعْ فِيْ الُعِذْقِ , وَلَا عَامْ اَلسَّنَةْ
You do not amputate when there is famine,
You do not apply the Hadd(حدّ) of As-Sarqah(السرقة), of stealing when there is famine.
If people are stealing to live their hand are not amputated.
The hands of burglar is amputated when they can live, but they are still stealing.
But if somebody is, stealing for the sole purpose of just surviving,
then in this situation, even though it is Haram(حرام),
but the Hadd(حدّ) of amputation is not applied.
And that is what happened during the time Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
An important lesson to learn from this.
You know, sometimes we get to carried away and we say that you know, if we would just apply Sharia(شريعة),
Allah would flood us with blessings and we would all become rich
and we would all own brand new Mercedes Benz or BMW's.
We would have these huge mansions.
All what we have to do is apply Shariah(شرية) and we're all going to become rich and wealthy,
and sometimes such promises are made.
You know sometimes when you have elections in some Muslim countries and the Islamists would say,
we will solve economical problems, we'll take care of your needs, we will do this and that?
Is that something that Rasool Allah ﷺ did
or is it something that the Sahabahرضى الله عنهم promised their followers.
Did they say just become Muslim in your pocket will be loaded ?
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was discussing the terms of Bay'ah Ul-Aqabah(بيعةالعقبه) the Pledge of Allegiance with Al-Ansaar(الانصار),
this is one of the most important treaties or agreements that Rasool Allah ﷺ was involved in.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking the Ansaar(أنْصَار) to commit their lives and their wealth
that's not a very easy commitment.
It's not easy to go to some people and tell them,
I want you to put your life and wealth on the line.
It's impossible, to ask somebody to do that.
That's what Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking the Ansaar(أنْصَار), he was telling them.
I want you to protect me just like you protect your wives and your children.
Do you agree? They said: Yes! We are agree.
One of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار)  stood up and said, listen
you understand the implications of this agreement.
This means that the Arabs and non Arabs are going to come against you,
this is not something to be taken lightly.
And then he said: You either promise him and fulfill that promise or pull out of it now, before it's too late.
You don't have to commit there's no agreement yet, we didn't give our word yet.
So, pull out of it now, this is the Al-Habbab Al-Mundhir(الحبَّاب المنذر),
and Al-Abbas(العباس) had some similar words, he said Muhammad(محمد) is protected among his people
and you are the one inviting him to your land.
Are you sure that you're able to protect him?
So, all warnings were given to Al-Ansaar(الانصار) afore time.
They knew it very well, Al-Habbab Al-Mundhir(الحبَّاب المنذر), told them that,
Al Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبدالمطلب) told them that,
you are getting your hands in hot water.
What did Al-Ansaar(الانصار) say?
They said: All right that's our part of the bargain.
What will we get?
What is our part?
You see, our commitment to this agreement is, we put our lives and wealth on the line.
What will you give us in exchange?
Did Rasool Allah ﷺ tell them I promise you five ministries in the government?
Did he tell them I will promise you this number of seats in the parliament?
Did he tell them that I promise you half of the wealth?
Did he tell them I will make you kings after me?
Like for example with Rabiyyah(ربيعة), when Rasool Allah ﷺ was discussing with them,
because Rasool Allah ﷺ went to meet many different tribes and they all turned him down,
but this tribe from Iraq, they said: This man if we take him with us
we can eat with him, the Arabs and the non Arabs.
They saw some abilities in Muhammadﷺ. They said: We could use him
we could use him for our benefit.
So, when they were discussing with Muhammadﷺ.
Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه told them: What he expects from them. They said;
We agree as long as you give us the kingdom after you.
As long as you transfer power to us, after you pass away.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ say:? He said;
اِنَّا الْاَرْضَ لله يُوْرِثُهَا مَنْ يَشَاءُ وَلْعَاقِبَةُ الْمُتَّقِيْنَ۝
This earth belongs to Allah and Allah will give it to whomever He wills,
and the end belongs to the pious.
In the end, the victorious will be the Muttaqeen(متقين).
But Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying: This is something, I cannot commit to.
This is something in the hands of Allah, I cannot promise you kingdom and power.
This is something that belongs to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, I don't have that authority.
So, the Al-Ansaar(الانصار) are saying, what are you going to give us?
because it's an agreement.
there's a transaction, exchange.
We are going to give our lives and our wealth.
What are we going to get back.?
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ say:?
One word, Al-Jannah(الجنة)! Paradise.
That’s all what can I offer you.
What did they say?
قَالُوْ رَبَيْهَ الْبَيْعَ لَا نَقِيْلُوْ وَلَا نَسْتَقِيْلَ
They said: What a profitable trade, we will never give up.
What is better than Jannah(جنة).
They said: This is the best deal we could ask for.
لا نقيلو ولا نستقيل
You will never find us backing out of it.
We will be there and they were true to their word.
Al-Ansaar(الانصار) they fought until the last moment
they gave their lives to Rasool Allah ﷺ, everything.
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tests you in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) one of the greatest of Al-Khulafah(ألخلفاء)
but still a famine occurred during his reign,
people were dying due to hunger.
So, you cannot really promise people Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
You I cannot tell them that I'm going to offer you Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
That's not something in your hands.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and the Muslims were tested. He said:
إِبْتُلِيْتُمْ بِيْ وَ أُبْتَلِيْتُ بِكُمْ
He said: I am tested through you and you're tested through me.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه was worried maybe this is because of my sins,
Maybe it's because of your sins.
He said: This is happening to us either because of my sins or your sins or the sins of all of us.
So, make Tauba(توبة) and ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to forgive you
and that would be his Dua(دُعَا) in Assalaat-Ul-Asqaa(الصلاة استسقاء)
and in the Khutub(خطب) that he would give, he would keep on saying:
اَسْتَغْفِرُاللهَ وَ اَتُوْبُ اِلَيْهَ، اَسْتَغْفِرُاللهَ وَ اَتُوْبُ اِلَيْهَ، اَسْتَغْفِرُاللهَ وَ اَتُوْبُ اِلَيْهَ،
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says in Qur'an in Sur'at Nooh(سورة نوح),
اِسْتَغْفِرُوا رَبّكُمْ إِنَّهُ كَانَ غَفَّارًا ۝ يُرْسِل السَّمَاء عَلَيْكُمْ مِدْرَارًا۝
وَيُمْدِدْكُمْ بِأَمْوَالٍ وَبَنِينَ وَيَجْعَلْ لَكُمْ جَنَّاتٍ وَيَجْعَلْ لَكُمْ أَنْهَارًا۝
Ask Allah  forgiveness, Allah is forgiving, He would send down rain on you from the sky.
So, forgiveness in Assalaat-Ul-Asqaa(الصلاة استسقاء) you make Istaghfar(أستغفار).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was very sensitive.
He would see that natural occurrences are influenced by your actions.
So, when there was an earthquake in Madina during the reign of Umar(عُمَر)
and then the earthquake happened again.
He stood on the pulpit and he gathered the Muslims and he said;
"This earthquake is because of your sins and if this earthquake happens a third time, I'm going to leave you.
" I'm leaving, I'm getting, I'm walking out of Madina.
He said: You either stop these sins or I'm going to leave.
So, he used to see that, this is because of what the people are doing.
So, that could happen to the best.
Why?
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ purifies the best,
you see with the Kafir(كافر), Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ rewards them for their good in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
So, that they will meet him on the Day of Judgment without any good deeds.
And the believer Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ punishes him in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) for his sins.
So, that he meets Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on the Day of Judgment without any sins.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: If loves the person he would test him through trials and tribulations in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
So, that he would be walking on the face of the earth without any sins, cleansed.
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ was testing Umar(عُمَر) and Allah was testing the Muslims and they were dying, famine.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) the same year another crisis or catastrophe occurred in Ash-Sham(ألشام)
in the 18 year of Hijrah(هجرة) and that was the plague of Umwaas(عمواس), Ta'oon Amwaas(طاعون عمواس)
Amwaas(عمواس), is a town next to Jerusalem.
Amwaas(عمواس) is a village close to Jerusalem Al-Qudus(القدس)
and that's where the plague started and it just spread out all over Ash-sham(ألشام)
claiming the lives of the population of Ash-sham(ألشام) many of the Muslims died.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was on his way to Ash-sham(ألشام) and they told him, that there's a plague
and they told him, don't go to Ash-sham(ألشام).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) made Shuraa(شورى), consultation with the Sahabah(صحابه),
some of them said: You go, some said, you don't.
For example Muslima Al-Fath(مسلمة الفتح), the late Muslims they all said: Don't go.
Some of the early Muslims they said: This is the Qadar( القدر) of Allah, just go.
Abdur Rahman Bin Auf( عبدالرحمن بن عوف) came and said;
I have a Hadith(حديث) from Rasool Allah ﷺ, regarding that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إِذَا سَمِعْتُمْ بِهَذَا الْوَبَاءْ بِبَلَدٍ(بِطَّاعُوْنِ فِيْ الاَرْضٍ) فَلَا تَقْدِمُوْا عَلَيْهِ
وَإِذَا وَقَعَ(بِاالاَرْضٍ) بِبَلَدٍوَأَنْتُمْ فِيْهِ فَلَا تَخْرِجُوْافِرَارًا مِّنْه
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(ألمسلم), Abdur Rahman Bin Auf(عبدالرحمن بن عوف) said;
If you hear about the plague in a town… do not enter it,
and if you are already there… Do not leave.
So, if you're outside don't go inside, if you're inside do not leave
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), this is the modern day, quarantine
you do not allow anything to come from outside
and in the same time, you don't allow the people who are infected from leaving.
So, this is the proper health regulation nothing comes in and nothing goes out.
So, when there is a Hadith(حديث) from Rasool Allah ﷺ, the Sahabah(صحابه) agreed
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) went back to Madina.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه sent a letter to Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
Umar(عُمَر) used to love Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
He used to love him so much.
So, he sends him a letter, he said;
سَلَامٌ عَلَيْكَ,أَمَّا بَعْدَ، فَإِنَّه’ قَدْ عَرَضَتْ لِيْ حَاجَةْ أُشَافِهَكْ فِيْهَا
فَعَزَمْتُ عَلَيْكَ إِذَا نَظَرْتَ فِيْ كِتَابِيْ هَذَا أَلَّاتَضَعْه’ مِنْ يَدِكَ حَتَّى تُقْبِلَ إِلَيً,
He said: I have something that I want to talk to you about and
I have to do it verbally face to face.
So, when you receive this letter from me, do not drop it, until you come here.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) understood, what Umar(عُمَر) meant by that.
Umar(عُمَر) was trying to pull Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) out.
Abu Obaidah رضي الله عنه, because he wasn't affected yet
and maybe the plague didn't reach that area yet.
So, Umar(عُمَر) wanted him to come out.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) sent him a letter back. He said;
يَا اَمِيْرُ الْمُو مِنِيْنَ إِنِّيْ قَدْ عَرَفْتُ حَاجَتَكَ إِلَيّْ وَإِنِّيْ فِيْ جُنْدٍ مِّنَّ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ لَا أَجِدُبِنَفْسِيْ رَغْبَةً عَنْهُمْ
فَلَسْتُ أُرِيْدُ فِرَاقَهُمْ حَتَّى يَقْضِيْ اللهُ فِيْيَ وَفِيْهِمْ أَمْرَه’ وَقَضَاهْ ,
فَحَلِّلْنِيْ مِنْ عَزْمَتِكَ يا أمير المومنين وَدَعْنِيْ فِيْ جُنْدِيْ
He said:, O, Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I know, why you want me to come.
I know why you want me to come.
But I'm among my soldiers,
I'm among my soldiers.
And I don't want to give myself preference over them.
What is going to happen to them is going to happen to me
and I'm going to stay with them until, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ brings down his Qadha'a(قضاء),
brings down his judgment.
So, please, Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) excuse me,
and allow me to stay behind.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) did not want to desert his soldiers,
you either call us all back or I'm going to stay with them.
If they die, we die together.
But I'm not going to leave my soldiers.
So, Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) because of his loyalty towards his soldiers, he lost his life.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) died in that plague.
He could've ran away, he had time to leave,
but he didn't want to leave the Muslim soldiers
and definitely Umar(عُمَر) is not gonna call back all of the Muslim soldiers from Ash-sham(ألشام).
That was frontier land, outposts, lands of Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), how can you call them all back?
So, the plague claimed the life of Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة),
it claim the life of Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل),
it claimed the life of Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiyan(يزيد إبن أبي سُفيان),
Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو), Utba Bin Sohail Ibn Amr(عتبة بن سهيل إبن عمرو)
many of the Sahabah(صحابه).
In fact, 20,000 Muslims died in the plague of Amwaas(عمواس),
and that is almost half of the Muslim population of Ash-Sham(ألشام).
It was a disaster.
And if the Romans took advantage of that, maybe they could have re-occupied Ash-sham(ألشام).
But, Subhan Allah, Allah kept them away.
Half of the Muslim soldiers in Ash-Sham(ألشام) died in that Plague.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ says that "the plague is a shahadah(شهادة) for my Ummah(امة)."
Plague is martyrdom for them.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ chose them for martyrdom.
Because in At-Tabri(الطبري) if these narrations are correct.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) saw the plague spreading around his soldiers, and it didn't affect him.
So, he made the Dua(دُعَا) and He said:, O, Allah! Where is my share of the plague?
And immediately after that he was infected.
And then Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل) was so upset
because of the death of Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) because he loved him.
He was the one who was mostly affected, by the death of Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة)
he was his friend they were both in Ash-sham(ألشام), so that greatly affected him.
So, when he saw his brother Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة), dying as a shaheed(شهيد) in the plague.
He said: O Allah where's my share of the plague.
Immediately, after that his Son Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) got infected and his son died.
Muadh(معاذ) went to his son and he said: O my son have patience, have patience, his son said;
يَا اَبَتِيْ قَالَ سَتَجِدُنِي إِنْ شَاءَ اللَّهُ صَابِرًا وَلَا أَعْصِي لَكَ أَمْرًا۝
He responded with the same response that Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) said to his father,
when he told him, I'm going to sacrifice you.
O my father, you will find me In sha Allah(إن شاء الله) patient.
So, he passed away and then Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل) was infected and he died.
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذ إبن جبل) said: O Allah, You know that I don't want to live in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
for the sake of owning farms and increasing my Wealth,
the only reason why I want to live, is to fast the long days of summer
and to pray the long nights of winter.
That's the only reason why I want to be in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), not to gather wealth
it is to get closer to You, O Allah.
And if this is the time for me to meet you, I welcomed that appointment.
THE FINANCIAL SITUATION OF THE KHILAFAH(خِلَافَه).
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
وَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّمَا غَنِمْتُمْ مِنْ شَيْءٍ فَأَنَّ لِلَّهِ خُمُسَهُ وَلِلرَّسُولِ وَلِذِي الْقُرْبَىٰ وَالْيَتَامَىٰ وَالْمَسَاكِينِ وَابْنِ السَّبِيلِ
إِنْ كُنْتُمْ آمَنْتُمْ بِاللَّهِ وَمَا أَنْزَلْنَا عَلَىٰ عَبْدِنَا يَوْمَ الْفُرْقَانِ يَوْمَ الْتَقَى الْجَمْعَانِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ۝
Al-Anfal(ألأنفال) Verse 41, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
"And know that out of all the booty that you may acquire, in war,
a fifth share is assigned to Allah,
and to the messenger and to the near relatives, orphans, the needy, and the wayfarer,
if you do believe in Allah, and in the revelation
we sent down to our servant on the day of testing
the day of the meeting of the two forces for Allah has power over all things."
This Ayah(آية) reveals the Hukum(حكم), the ruling on Ghanimah(غنيمه),
Ghanimah(غنيمه) is the spoils of war.
It states that one fifth of the spoils of war
goes to Allah, Rasool Allah ﷺ, the Miskeen(مسكين), Ibn Sabeel(إبن سبيل), and the Yateem(يتيم).
The other four fifths go to the fighters.
So, for example, if you had, let's say 100 pounds, 80 pounds would go to the fighters
and then those 80 pounds are going to be split among the fighters.
The horseman gets one share for himself and two shares for his horse
and the foot soldier gets one share.
The 20% or the 20 pounds that is going to Allah,
Rasool Ullah, the Yateem(يتيم) the Ibn Sabeel(إبن سبيل) and Al-Miskeen(مسكين)
is split into five, so 20% by five is 4%.
So, 4% goes to Allah, 4% goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ
4% to the Yateem(يتيم), four% to the orphan I mean Yateem(يتيم)
and 4% goes to the poor and 4% Ibn Sabeel(إبن سبيل), the wayfarer.
That's the ruling on Ghanimah(غنيمه).
Now, when we say it goes to Allah
Rasool Allah ﷺ spends his 4% and the 4% that goes to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, as he deems fit.
So, it is Rasool Allah ﷺ who spends it
في مصالحل المسلمين
what benefits the Muslims.
Ghanimah(غنيمه) there's something called Ghanimah(غنيمه) and there is Fae(فيئ).
Fae(فيئ) is what you take from the enemy without a fight.
Ghanimah(غنيمه) is what is taken from the enemy through war.
And this is an issue of Fiqh(فقه) that we're talking about because
there was a discussion that occurred between Umar(عُمَر) and The Sahabah(صحابه)
a very important discussion that occurred between them
and it took a long time for them to sort it out.
The ruling is that when there is a war and the Muslim army wins,
they have the right to claim everything that they lay their hands on as their property
including the people.
So, the land, the money and the people become property for the Muslims
and that is then split, according to these rules.
That is what Rasool Allah ﷺ did in Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
that's what he did in the Ghazawaat(غزوات)
that's the rule of Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
Now, in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) the Muslims opened vast, wealthy areas, Al Iraq, Ash-sham(ألشام) and Egypt.
These were the jewels of the world in those days,
the Roman and Persian Empire would fight over these lands because they are so lucrative.
These are the fertile lands.
Egypt because of the Nile, Al-Iraq because of the Euphrates River
and then Ash-sham(ألشام) the Holy Land because of his religious significance
but it's also blessed land is very fertile and blessed land very wealthy.
So, the Roman Empire was in control of Egypt and Ash-sham(ألشام)
and the Persian Empire was in control of Al-Iraq.
When the Muslims opened these Lands,
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) and Muad Ibn Jabal(معاذبن جبل) they came to  the Khalifah(خليفه) and they said;
If you gonna split up the land among the Muslims.
So, you're splitting up the land and the people and everything among the Muslims.
Muslims are going to own huge properties
and then they're going to die and this will be inherited by their children
and then inherited by the children of their children and it will go down the line
and money will be accumulated within the hands of a few.
I mean we were talking about huge pieces of land and these are very small armies.
So, one soldier will end up owning towns.
So, they said: You need to find a solution.
Because after that how gonna we finance our Ghazawat(غزوات),
if all of this money gets accumulated as private property, among the soldiers.
How will you finance your campaigns?
So, they were concerned about the continuation of Ghazuu(غزؤ).
How will Ghazuu(غزؤ) carry on in the future
if Iraq, Ash-sham(ألشام) and Egypt is split up among the soldiers.?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he considered these thoughts
from Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذبن جبل) and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف),
and it was becoming appealing to him.
So, he called an assembly,
the Sahabah(صحابه) came and he discussed the issue with them.
Some of the Sahabah(صحابه) like Bilal(بلال) and Zubair(زبير), they said: No way.
We're not going to allow somebody to take the property that we claimed through our own swords.
No way will we give it to somebody who didn't attend this Ghazuu(غزؤ) with us,
why should they get it.?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he saw resistance from some of the Sahabah(صحابه),
he called in some of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار),
I actually read it to you the statements of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
He started by reciting what he sees, what he views as the evidence to support his case.
And these are the Ayaat(آيات) from Surat Al-Hashar(سورة الحشر):
"What Allah has bestowed on His messenger and taken away from them
for this he made no expedition with either cavalry or camelry.
But Allah gives power to his messengers over any He pleases,
and Allah has power over all things".
So, Allah here is talking about the wealth, that's taken from the enemies of Allah
and put in the hands of Rasool Ullah.
How was that split?
it says: This is from verse six to 10, let me read them.
"What Allah has bestowed on His messenger, and taken away from the people of the townships
belongs to Allah to His Messenger, and to the kindred and orphans,
the needy, and the wayfarer, in order that it may not merely make a circuit between the wealthy among you.
So, take what the messenger assigns to you,
and deny yourself that which He withhold from you and fear Allah, for Allah is strict in punishment.
Some part is due to the indigent Mohajer(مهاجر)'s
those who were expelled from their homes and their property
while seeking grace from Allah and His good pleasure
and aiding Allah and His Messenger such are indeed the sincere ones.
So the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) have a claim to fae(فيئ),
but those who before them, had homes in Madina, and had adopted the faith
show their affection to such as came to them for refuge
and entertain no desire in their hearts for things given to the latter,
but give them preference over themselves,
even though poverty was their own lot, and those saved from the covetousness of their souls.
They are the ones that achieve prosperity."
This is talking about Al-Ansaar(الانصار),
And those who came after them, and say: Our Lord, forgive us
and our brethren who came before us into the faith,
and leave not in our hearts, rancor or sense of injury against those who have believed.
Our Lord, You are indeed full of kindness most merciful.
To summarize what these Ayaat(آيات) are saying regarding the fae(فيئ),
it goes to the Muhajireen(مهاجرين), the Ansaar(أنْصَار) and the ones who come after them.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is saying that the ones who come after you have a claim to the fae(فيئ).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
وَاللهِ لَا يُفْتَحْ بَعْدِيْ بَلَدْ فَيَكُوْنُ فِيْهِ كَبِيْرَ نَيْلٍ بَلْ عَسَى أَنْ يَكُوْنَ كَلَّا عَلَى الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ،
فَإِذَا قَسَّمْتُ أَرْضَ الْعِرَاقِ بِعَلُوْجِهَا, وَأَرْضُ الشَّامِ بِعَلُوْجِهَا, فَمَايَسَدُّ بِهِ الثُّغُورْ؟
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
I don't think that any land we're going to open after this, will be as wealthy as this land.
In fact, the land that we may open in the future will be a liability for us,
it will be a burden on us,
we will open it for Da'wah(دعوة) but in terms of the wealth it will be a burden on us
because these are the richest lands.
So, if I split Al-Iraq, and it's Ulooj(علوج).
Ulooj(علوج) are the non believers of Al- Iraq, if I split Al-Iraq and its Ulooj(علوج)
and Asham(ألشام) and its Ulooj(علوج), then how will we finance the outposts?
How will we finance our camps, the military camps.
وَمَا يَكُوْنُ للِذُّرِّيَّةْ وَالْأَرَامِلْ لِهَذَا الْبَلَدْ وَبِغَيْرِهِ مِنْ أَرَاضِي الشَّامِ وَالْعِرَاقْ؟
And how will the orphans and widows live in this land and in Iraq and Ash-sham(ألشام),
if all of the land is already split up.
فَأَكْثَرُا عَلَى عمر
So, they resisted that idea fiercely.
They said;
تَقِفْ مَا أَفَاءْ اَللهُ عَلَيْنَا بِأَسْيَافِنَا عَلَى قَوْمِ لَّمْ يَحْضُرُوْا وَلَمْ يَشْهَدُوْا,
وَلأَبْنَاءِ الْقَوْمْ وَأَبْنَائِهِمْ وَلَمْ يَحْضَرُوْا
You want to give the land that we opened with our own swords
to people who did not witness this opening.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: This is but an opinion.
This is just an opinion.
And then they said: Well then you seek counsel.
So, he invited 10 of the leaders of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار), Al Aos wal- Khazraj(ألأوس ولخزرج)  and he said;
I'm one of you and you can see that some accepted my suggestion while some rejected it
and I don't want you to follow me just because I like this idea.
I want you to follow it because you believe it’s the truth.
He said: Tell me what is your opinion. He said;
وَلَكِنْ رَّأَيْتُ أَنَّه’ لَمْ يَبْقَ شَيْء يُفْتَحْ بَعْدَ أَرْضَ كِسْرَى وَقَدْ غَنِمْنَا الله أَمْوَالَهُمْ وَأَرْضَهُمْ وَعَلُوْجَهُمْ
فَقَسَّمْتُ مَا غَنَمُوْا وَمِنْ أَمْوَالِهِمْ بَيْنَ أَهْلِهْ
He said: The land of Kisra(كسرى), I have taken all of the wealth and I already split among you.
So, the wealth was split among them it was just the land and the people.
The people were not enslaved and the land was still in their hands.
He said;
وَقَدْ رَأَيْتُ أَنْ أَحْبِسَ الْأَرْضِيْنَ بِعَلُوْجِهَا وَاضِعًا عَلَيْهِمْ فِيْهَا الْخِرَاجْ وَفِيْ رِقَابِهِمِ الْجِزْيَةْ
My suggestion is that all of this land becomes public property owned by the government
and the owners, the former owners, the disbelievers who owned that land carry on working in it
And they pay Al-Jizya(الجزية) and they pay a tax on the land, called Al-Kharaj(الخراج).
So this was a new suggestion, but they pay a tax on the land.
أَرَأَيْتُمْ هَذِهِ الثَغُوْرَ لَا بُدَّ لَهَا مِنْ رِجَالٍ يَلْزَمُوْنَهَا,
أَرَأَيْتُمْ هَذِهِ الْمُدَنِ ألْعِظَامْ لَا بُدَّ لَهَا مِنْ أَنْ تُشْحِنَ بِالْجُيُوْشَ
He said: Do you see all of these outposts they need to be filled with soldiers.
Do you see all of these great towns, they need to be protected.
Who's going to pay for this?
So, the concern was how to spread the Da'wah(دعوة), how to carry on,
with the Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
They said the opinion is yours
and if you don't do that, then the people of Kuffr(كفر) are going to come back to those towns.
They said: We agree with you,
because if you don't, then there will be nobody to guard those towns
and the kuffar will come back to them.
So, this was the rise of the Muslim professional army.
In the beginning in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ and in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
you didn't have professional soldiers.
What you had, is the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, who are Civilians,
they were the ones doing the fighting whenever the Imam(اِمَام) would give them the orders.
But now, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wants to appoint dedicated soldiers
to the outpost and to guard the new Muslim towns
and they need salaries and that's why you find that armies consume a lot of Money,
they claim a major part of the budget of any nation
and this burden was beginning to appear in the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
when there was the nucleus of the professional army.
So, he wanted to find money to finance that and this money would come from the land
and from Al-Jizya(الجزية).
So, that's where Kharaaj(خراج) came from.
The first to apply the rule of Kharaaj(خراج) was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
now again did he innovate in that or is this something that has its origins in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
First of all he quoted the Ayaat(آيات) and he saw these Ayaat(آيات) as an evidence for him.
Now, you might say well Rasool Allah ﷺ he, divided the Ghanimah(غنيمة) among the fighters
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not do that.
The answer would be that it is allowed to claim the land and the people and divided them among the soldiers
but it's not mandatory to do so,
because Rasool Allah ﷺ did not do that when he opened Makkah.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah,
he did not claim the land and he did not enslaved the people.
Therefore this is the evidence that it is an option and it's not mandatory to do that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ set that people of Makkah free and he did not claim their land.
So, no Ghanimah(غنيمه), was taken from Makkah.
So, that's evidence to support Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) in what he has done,
add to that the Shura(شورى),
this was a decision that is reached through Shura(شورى).
So, that's regarding Al-Kharaaj(ألخراج).
And Al-Kharaj(ألخراج) was one of the greatest sources of income to the Muslim Treasury.
And another new financial resource in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
one of the Muslim leaders came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and said;
The non Muslims are charging us, Customs - when we enter into their land to do business.
Should we charge them.?
They were charging customs on any Muslim businessmen,
who are going into their lands.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: How much do they charge you? He said: 10%
He said, well you charge them, 10%.
So, this was the first time non Muslims were charged, when they enter into Muslim land to do business.
That wasn't the case in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ or the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
but Umar(عُمَر) wanted to treat them equally since they are charging our businessmen,
to have a fair trade agreement we need to charge them too,
otherwise we would be at a disadvantage.
They come and do business in our land and they don't pay any customs while we paying 10%.
And this is called Al-Ushr(العشر).
Al-Ushr(ألعشر) means one tenth.
So, he started applying this charge on any non Muslims who would enter into the Muslim land to do business.
Then you had Al-Ghanaem(ألغنائم), Al-Ghanaem(ألغنائم) were also a source of income.
So, Al-Ghanimah(غنيمه) is the wealth that is taken,
and Al-Kharaj(ألخراج) is the money that is taken from the land, from the harvest.
So Al-Kharaj(ألخراج) he would apply for example, out of a certain area of grape vines,
you pay 10 Dirham(درهم), if it's dates you pay five Dirham(درهم) and so on
Al-Ghanimah(غنيمه) is the wealth that is taken from the army
and from the people that's called Ghanimah(غنيمه).
And Ghanimah(غنيمه), when it came to KISRA(كسرى),
The Romans and Persians in general, when they would go to fight they would go on with their wealth
for example, they would have gems, diamonds, gold,
their swords would have these treasures on them.
So, a lot of that was claimed by the Muslim army, and the amounts were huge.
For example, in the palace of Kisra(كسرى) they found this carpet or rug
it was three thousand six hundred 3600 Diraah(دراع) long.
And Diraah(دراع) is something like a foot or even longer than a foot.
So, we are talking about a huge rug.
And the amazing thing about this rug is, it was three dimensions,
it had statues in it and it had rivers flowing, it had animals and none of them were real.
The water that was flowing or the rivers was gold.
The animals were treasures, diamonds and gems, the mountains were silk.
We are talking about the three dimension rug and it's packed with all of these valuables.
They sold it and it fetched 20,000 Dirham(درهم)
and they cut it into pieces, so Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) had a piece
and other Sahabah(صحابه) has a piece.
They weren't interested in keeping this huge rug as a souvenir or hanging it in Madina somewhere.
They cut it into pieces and sold it.
What's the use of having this, use it for Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
For Example the Ghanimah(غنيمه) would be so much that at one point of time.
The share of the soldier would be 15000 Dirham(درهم), which was huge amount of money.
In Jaloolaah(جلولأء), the Ghanimah(غنيمه) was six Million.
May be the effect of all of this wealth coming in, didn’t show up in the time of Umar(عُمَر) there is a lag.
But it showed up in the time of Uthman(عثمان).
The Ghazawat(غزوات) happened in the time of Umar(عُمَر)
but the fruits were showing in the time of Uthman رضي الله عنه.
That’s when the Muslims were becoming very wealthy,
and that’s when, when you had people like Abu Darda(ابودرداء) and Abu Dharr(ابو زر)
going around warning the Muslims from Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Abu Darda(ابودرداء) he would Stand in the square in Damascus and he would call the Muslims
and saying: O people of Demashq(دمشق): Don’t you have Taqwa(تقوى).
Don’t you see what happened to the people of Aad(عاد),
Didn’t you see what happened to the people of Thamood(ثمود),
aren’t you afraid that the same fate will befall you.
He is reminding them about what happens to you when you are living a life of luxury.
Alright, we'll close with that and we'll carry on In Sha Allah(إن شاء الله) next week.
We'll continue talking about the finances of the Khilafah(خِلَافَه), financial issues.
We'll also talk about the judicial system in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه,
and that will probably take us a few days and then we'll move on to the Ghazawaat(غزوات),
the Ghazawaat(غزوات) will be the last thing, we'll talk about Ghazawaat(غزوات) of Al-Iraq,
Iran and As-Sham(ألشام) and Egypt.
Tayeb(طيب), some of the questions.
Sorry I didn't bring the questions that I had from last night
I sorted them out but I forgot to bring them, so I'll just read the questions that I have here.
And we'll take some verbal questions In Sha Allah(إن شاء الله).
My wife is pregnant, but she doesn't want the child now.
My mother says I am too young to be a father. What shall I do, I'm 20 years old.
Today maybe people mature too late.
So 20 years old are still supposed to be playing Xbox and PlayStation.
Going to the arcade, they're not mature yet.
But in the old days, 14, 15 years old and you join the army and you go and fight.
That was the case with Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر)
and some of the other Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
So, at the age of 15 You're seen as a full grown adult, and you're ready to get married,
ready to have kids, ready to start family.
So 20 years old brother يعني, if we're gonna go with the average that Rasool Allah ﷺ set for the Ummah(امة) of Muhammad(محمد),
that the ages of this Ummah(امة) are between 60 and 70.
1/3 of your life is already gone.
So when are you going to have kids if you're not going to have them now.
Anyway, she's already pregnant, and what you're saying here is not a valid reason
to have an abortion if that's what you're referring to,
because that's the only thing I can understand from this.
Your mother doesn't want the child, your wife doesn't want the child.
So what to do is, and I guess that's you're implying that
you're asking whether an abortion is allowed or not.
An abortion is only allowed if it is prior to 42 days.
And there needs to be a valid reason for having it,
the health of the mother or some scholars would say, situations like forced rape or things like that.
It is allowed before 42 days because after 42 days, it is a living human being.
يُنْفَخُ فِيهِ الرُّوحُ
According to the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ , the soul enters the body at the age of 42 days,
so it will be considered killing a human being after that stage.
However, before 42 days, even though it is not considered to be alive yet.
This not a valid reason to have that, you should have Taqwa(تقوى) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and you should have Tawakkal(توكل) on Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
It was something that was destined and ordained and it happened.
And you say Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), and your wife should just be patient and wait,
and she is here.
Believe me, sister as soon as you have that child, you will love that child
because you will be the mother of that child
and Allah will put in your heart, the love of your child
and you would regret even thinking about this.
At that moment, you will say, You will regret that you had these thoughts
you just wait and be patient and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will provide for this child
you're not the one who's providing for him, or her.
It is Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, Who gives the Rizq(رزق).
In fact, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) the child brings along his Rizq(رزق).
And you as a parents sometimes live off, their Rizq(رزق), You live off their Rizq(رزق)
Allah sends Rizq(رزق) to them
and because it's coming to them and they're in your house, you take part of it.
I know, a brother, he got married, he received a salary raise.
He had his first child, salary raise,
second child, salary raise,
third child, salary raise.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) the timing was exact, Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
And this brother is spending on himself from that salary raise,
when it is clear that is for his child and he is spending from that money.
And now he had the fourth.
So Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم) what will happen.
So tell your mother that you're 20 years old.
You are Old!! Mom I am old.
Why did she get you married, if you are too young.?
Q: If we get the divorce in English court, is that a divorce in Islam,
if so, is that first, second or third Talaq(طلاق).?
The divorce, needs to be done Islamically.
Then if you if it needs to be done in the court for some other legal reasons.
Than that's something different but it needs to be done Islamically,
divorce needs to be done Islamically.
So it doesn't count.
However, one needs to be careful you cannot generalize in all of these situations.
This is an interesting question, because I'm running out of questions that's why reading these, otherwise,
Assalam O Alaikum(اسلام علیکم) I want to ask,
why is it obligatory for sisters to cover their face and not brothers.?
Again I wouldn't have read this question if I had some other questions to go through.
Brothers and sisters! We follow the law the Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ because Allah said so.
I'm not reading this question because it's a joke. I'm reading it because there is an important
thing that we need to learn and it's so important that this is the essence of Islam.
It's the essence of Islam and that is Tasleem(تسليم).
A Muslim is not a Muslim if they don't have Tasleem(تسليم).
You don't have to prove everything through an empirical experiment to follow it.
In Islam we follow things that we don't know why. And that is Emaam Bil Ghaeb(إيمان بالغيب).
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, the first thing is Surat Ul-Baqarah(سورة البقرة).
الم  ۝ ذَٰلِكَ الْكِتَابُ لَا رَيْبَ  فِيهِ  هُدًى لِلْمُتَّقِينَ ۝
There is no doubt in this book and its guidance for Al-Muttaqeen(ألمتقين),
what are their qualities.? The first thing, Allah said about them,
الَّذِينَ يُؤْمِنُونَ بِالْغَيْبِ
The ones who believe in the unseen. They believe they don't know it,
they didn't see it, they didn't hear it, they don’t smell it, they didn't taste it,
it's Ghaeb(ألغيب), it's unseen, unknown, they believe in it.
يُؤْمِنُونَ بِالْغَيْبِ
This is an important aspect of being a Muslim. And I'm saying it's the essence of Islam. Why?
Because that's where the name Islam comes.
We always talk about Islam, peace! Islam, peace! Really Islam is submission.
Salaam(سلام) is different. Islam(أسلام) means submission, Tasleem(تسليم).
When Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was sitting on his son Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and
he had the knife on his neck and he was about to sacrifice him.
What did Allah call that,
فَلَمَّا أَسْلَمَا
When when they were Muslim.
Allah called that Pastor Islam.
Why?
Because Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) are submitting to Allah
and doing something that they would not do otherwise.
They're doing something that they would not like to do,
but they're doing it for the sake of Allah because they submit to Allah.
That is Islam.
So, sisters, you do things because Allah said, so.
Brothers you do things because Allah said so.
And then we ask questions later.
Sometimes we don't know the answer.
We can speculate about the Hikmah(حكمة) of the Ibadaat(عبادات)
because many times the Ibadaat(عبادات) were mentioned without the Hikmah(حكمة).
Sometimes the Hikmah(حكمة) is mentioned.
كُتِبَ عَلَيْكُمُ الصِّيَامُ كَمَا كُتِبَ عَلَى الَّذِينَ مِنْ قَبْلِكُمْ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَتَّقُونَ ۝
Fasting was prescribed on you as it was prescribed on the nations before you
so that you would have Taqwa(تقوى).
So here the Hikmah(حكمة) was told to us.
You fast to have Taqwa(تقوى).
But we don't have the Hikmah(حكمة) told to us on anything and everything so we can speculate but that's about it.
So, the sister is told to have Hijab(حجاب) and the brother is not
because the sister has that attraction has that physical attraction
that the men don't have, and that's something with women.
They have that physical attraction, and that's not the case with men.
And when we say it's not the case with men, we're talking about in general terms.
But there are exceptions to every rule.
There are exceptions to every rule!
Yani(يعني) Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) we talked about that man, he shaved his head,
that’s Hijab(حجاب) for him, he put on an Imamah(إمامة), that was a Hijab(حجاب).
It is know there were two men in our history Waduhaa Al-Yeman(وضحى اليمن) and Al-Mukanna Al-Kindi(ألمُكَنَّا ألكِندي)
were men would go around with their faces covered, not to cause others Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
There were so handsome, they covered their faces.
So, these are issues, you're saying: O Allah I  love you, that's why I'm doing it.
I'm doing it because I love you and I want to please you.
I want you to be pleased with me and I'm going to do it, whether I like it or not.
I'm going to do it so that you would reward me for doing it.
So that should be our approach.
On Wednesday, you talked about the importance of knowing what is and what is not Haram(حرام) in your area of business.
I work in media and one part of my job is to promote the financial section of the paper.
This links in with the Haram(حرام) system of interest.
Would this make my job Haram(حرام).?
So maybe what you're talking about is the financial section,
so you'd talk about interest
you'd talk about banking system, you'd talk about this and that.
Allah Ho Alam(ألله أعلم) I cannot say exactly what's the ruling is here because
more would need to be known about the situation but
I would say that if you feel that there's something doubt for in there.
You've learned  a lot Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله) through your working through your education.
Take that with you and benefit the Muslims with it,
find something in which you could serve Ummah(امة) and do that,
Brothers or sisters! Try your best to work in something that benefits the Ummah(امة),
so that you at least can feel that I'm doing something that help in promoting the religion of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
You don't want to have your work life.
Absolutely separate from your religious life.
You want to have the two linked, correlate, so that you feel that spending these hours and hours
every day is something that is pleasing Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
always try to make that combination.
We have to pay Zakah(زكوة) on debt that you still have at this current moment in time
is a value greater than Nisaab(نصاب).
If you borrow money from me, I need to pay Zakah(زكوة) on it not you.
The one who lends pays the Zakah(زكوة), not the one, who borrows.
That's the rule.
Except if they say,
دَيْن لأ يُرجع صَدَادُو
Except if the debt you gave it to somebody who ripped you off
and you don't expect that he's gonna pay it back to you.
In this situation you do not pays Zakah(زكوة) on it.
If you expect to pay back, you have to pay Zakah(زكوة) every year.
If you're not expecting the money back, then you do not pay Zakah(زكوة) on it.
However if you do get it back, then you pay Zakah(زكواة) on all of the past years.
So that's the ruling.
When did Umar(عُمَر) sleep and for how long.?
Allah Ho Alam(ألله أعلم) you know, many of the personal details we don't know
for sure he didn't sleep a lot, he didn't sleep a lot.
But we don't know exactly when he would sleep.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE